Inventory of the Richardson family papers, 1870-1945
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Richardson family papers
1870-1945
Richardson family
00022
0.45 cubic ft. (1 document box + glass plate negatives)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
The collection contains materials related to the Richardson Family from 1870 to 1945, including ranch records (1886-1925), manuscripts of reminiscences written by Willing G. Richardson prior to 1945, and photographs and glass plate negatives of the Richardson Family, activities on the Richardson Ranch and in the surrounding area, and the University of Wyoming at Laramie, Wyoming.
Biography of the Richardson family
William Richardson (1847-1943) and Mary Jane Bloomer (1841-1910) were married in Carbon, Wyoming, in 1880. William Richardson was born in England and came to Carbon to work in the coal mines in 1875. Mary Jane Bloomer had previously been married to Norman Morley (d. 1862) in 1857 and William G. Stimpson (d. 1876) in 1874. She moved to Wyoming in 1868 and established a boarding house at Percy Station, near Fort Halleck in Carbon County. After Mary Jane and William were married, they established a cattle ranch near Elk Mountain in Carbon County, Wyoming. Their children were: Thomas D. (b. 1881), Edward L. (b. 1883), and Willing G. (1886-1968).
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials relating to the Richardson family from 1886-1945 including an account book (1886-1918); a journal of labor and ranch expenses (1891-1925); a register of livestock sold (1890-1921); and photographs of the Richardson family and ranch, and of the Carbon County, Wyoming area.
The collection also includes six manuscripts of reminiscences written by Willing G. Richardson around 1945 about Carbon County, William and Mary Jane Richardson, the Richardson family and ranch, and a local fur trapper known as "Old Tough."
The collection also contains 15 glass plate negatives of the Richardson Ranch, Elk Mountain, Edward L. Richardson, ranching activities of the Basin Land and Cattle Company and the University of Wyoming Mechanical Building from 1898-1902.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no other known archival collections created by the Richardson family at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The Richardson family papers were donated to the American Heritage Center by Willing G. Richardson between 1946 and 1961. A further accretion was donated by Allan Krafczic in 1973.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of select material from this collection are available at http://digitalcollections.uwyo.edu:8180/luna/servlet/uwydbuwy~68~68.
Access Terms
Richardson, William, 1847-1934.; Richardson, Mary Jane Bloomer, 1841-1910.; Richardson, Edward L., 1883-; University of Wyoming--Buildings.; Basin Land and Cattle Company.; Cattle trade--Wyoming--Carbon County.; Fur Traders--Wyoming--Carbon County.; Ranches--Wyoming--Carbon County.; Carbon County (Wyo.); Richardson Ranch (Wyo.); Elk Mountain (Wyo.); Wyoming--History--to 1889.; Wyoming--History--1890-1918.; Wyoming--History--1919-1945.; Business records.; Photographs.; Negatives.; Reminiscenses.;;; Richardson, Willing Gay.
Ranching; Pioneers; Immigration and American Expansion; Social Life and Customs; Home and Family; Wyoming
Container List
- Manuscripts by Willing Richardson, circa 1945, undated; Series I.
  - “Carbon”, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “The Country and People I Am Writing About”, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - “Life of William Richardson”, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “Old Tough, an Unforgettable Character”, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - “The Richardsons and Richardson Ranch”, circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - “To the Memory of Mrs. William Richardson”, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - “A Woman Who Lived a Pioneer Life and Loved It”, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Ranch Record Books, 1886-1925; Series II.
  - Account Book, 1886-1909 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1896-1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Labor and Ranch Expenses, 1891-1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sales of Live Stock and Hay, 1890-1921 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographs, 1870-1924; Series III.
  - Baker, F.M. – photographs by and of, circa 1890s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Battle Lake, 1870s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cabins – Jake Schmere and others, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Camp and Hunting Scenes, circa 1870-1903 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rod Williams; George Doane; etc.
  - Cherokee Trail, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Showing rocks laid by Indians to convey information
  - Deer and Elk, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    George Littlefield herd
  - Encampment, Wyoming, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Laramie, Wyoming, 1870, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes Laramie Furniture Company after fire
  - Roundup Scenes, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Medicine Bow Station; Beer Mug Ranch
  - Richardson Family, circa 1890s, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    William Richardson; Mary Jane Richardson and sons
  - Rock Creek, Wyoming, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - University of Wyoming, circa 1890s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Unidentified and Miscellaneous, 1903, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Mail carrier Fisher; Mr. and Mrs. Andrew Kortes and Lester Hunt; sheep by Elk Mountain; Conness bull; tie drive on Medicine Bow River; team and wagon by buttes
- Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1880s-1945; Series IV.
  - Descriptive list and prints, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Glass negatives nos. !-55 (some gaps), circa 1880s-1908 (Box Glass Negative Box)